<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Counsel to the true English, or, A word of advice to the Jacobites by a true member of the Church of England, as by law establish'd, in a letter to a friend.</title>
            <author>True member of the Church of England.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 35 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A34731</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C6516</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R15946</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11729539</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11729539</idno>
            <idno type="VID">48382</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A34731)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 48382)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 487:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Counsel to the true English, or, A word of advice to the Jacobites by a true member of the Church of England, as by law establish'd, in a letter to a friend.</title>
                  <author>True member of the Church of England.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 10 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for S. Manship,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jacobites.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:48382:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>COUNSEL TO THE True Engliſh: OR, A WORD OF ADVICE TO THE JACOBITES.</p>
            <p>By a True Member of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as by Law Eſtabliſh'd.</p>
            <p>In a Letter to a Friend.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Licenſed,</hi> May 22. 1691.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>S. Manſhip,</hi> at the <hi>Black Bull</hi> in <hi>Cornhill,</hi> M DC XCI.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="advice">
            <pb facs="tcp:48382:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:48382:2"/>
            <head>COUNSEL TO THE True Engliſh: OR A WORD OF ADVICE TO THE JACOBITES. In a Letter to a Friend.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOU are pleas'd to deſire my Opinion in reference to the Times, in anſwer whereunto I am the freer to impart my ſentiments, that (if true and juſt) they may be improved to the reforming the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous Judgments of others; and if I ſhould in any circumſtance be unhappily miſtaken, your kind Information may miniſter to my Conviction.</p>
            <p>In plain terms, the Face of <hi>England</hi> is very Squalid and Uncomfortable, and from her frequent Fluſhings, and from the many Contractions therein viſible, it is eaſie to gueſs ſome ſtrange malignity hath infected the Body, and that ſhe is thereby much out of order; ſuddain Startings, wild and extravagant Talking, panick Fears and Conſternations, ſecret Suſurrations and Whiſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, are infallible ſymptoms of an evil habit; and under theſe our Dear Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at this preſent Juncture ſorely laboureth: All which are imputed to the late Revolution, and as if ſo ſuddain a turn had brought upon her a
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:48382:3"/>
Vertigo, many of her Children are giddy, ſome ſtagger, and not a few are fallen from their beſt Reſolutions. It is my Opinion, That if this great Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>action were well conſidered and underſtood, what was not prevented might be yet amended; it is but common that ſtrange things ſhould raiſe admiration, but where an Extaſie or Diſtraction follows, the levity of Mens minds is blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able. The way I have thought expedient to raiſe the lapſed and confirm the unſtable, is to conſider, 1. The Occaſion requiring. 2. The Means introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing. 3. The Advantages depending upon this Change. The former will ſhew us our Ruin, Miſery and Deſolation intended: In the next we may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Providence juſtly, gently and ſeaſonably aſſiſting: And in the laſt (if we are wiſe) we may behold our Honour, Peace and Happineſs reſtored, and ſetled upon ſure and laſting Foundations.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Occaſion requiring and urging this Revolution.</p>
            <p>It is too unpleaſing a ſubject for the entertainment of any generous mind, (nor ſhall my Pen deſcribe the leaſt Scene of our Miſery with any ſuch inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) to reflect upon the perſon of a King, which all Nations acknowledg as Sacred. The Miſchances or Errours of Government, may with Moderation be conſidered apart from the Perſon in whoſe Reign they hapned, and truly at that unhappy time (which ought never to be forgotten) Religion, the one thing needful, was fallen below indifferent, and it was more commendable to profeſs none than the true; Vaſt Treaſures, Mountains of Wealth, and Rivers of humane Blood have been ſacrific'd in defence of Proteſtantiſm, which now became an unpardonable Crime to own, eſpecially in ſuch as ſtood Candidates for any Promotion; and what by the means of the foregoing vitiouſneſs and looſeneſs, together with the prevalency of Intereſt, many did ſo degenerate, that the favour of the Prince weighed down both the Love and Dread of God; and his Commiſſion was of more force than Gods Commands: yet theſe were the happy days which ſome nominal Proteſtants ſo heartily wiſh for again; it is no hard matter to gueſs their Zeal for the Truth, from their fond adhering to its Adverſary.</p>
            <p>I would willingly ask thoſe Irreligious Loyaliſts, what good, what comfort to Mind or Body, they could reaſonably promiſe themſelves or poſterity (<hi>qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentis</hi> Proteſtants) from a Government which had brought it ſelf under the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy neceſſity of introducing Popery; a Government which was oblig'd either to ſuppreſs the moſt pleaſing hopes of an unlimited Power, or elſe to ſet up Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try for its Support? This alone would quickly have been fatal to Realm; for we cannot be ignorant how Jealous God is of his Honour, how ſeverely he puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Iſraels</hi> deviations from the True Worſhip; What Miſeries, what Plagues, what Shame, what Captivity did their Spiritual Fornication bring upon them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And would not the ſame Means have produced the ſame Effects here as in <hi>Judea?</hi> How could any of us have hoped for the longer continuance of the Grace of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt among us, who muſt (having embraced the Romiſh Superſtition) detract from, and impair his Merits, by admitting the Servants into Co-partnerſhip with the Maſter in the great Work of the Mediati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and ſo deprive the Son of God of great part of his Honour to give it to the Children of Men?</p>
            <p>Have ſo many Laborious and Learned, Wiſe and Pious Volumes, by Gods Bleſſing and Mens Travail, been wrote to defend and juſtifie our Religion; and muſt theſe without detection of the leaſt Error, be condemned to Flames as Falſe and Erroneous? Have thoſe Holy Fathers who offered up their
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:48382:3"/>
Lives to Fire and Sword (rather than comply with the unjuſt and impious Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions of <hi>Rome</hi>) been honoured with the glorious name of Martyrs, and will their ungrateful Poſterity now prophanely Curſe that Title, and call them Hereticks and Rebels to the Spouſe of Chriſt? Yet this we muſt have come to, had Heaven tolerated the former Government longer. What has rob'd Truth of its Beauty, and put ſo charming a Vizard on Error, that our Arms are open for its Reception?</p>
            <p>Why ſhould Chriſtians become weary of Gods Reigning over them by his Spirit of Grace, and of a ſudden chooſe to ſubmit themſelves to the wiles, luſts and paſſions of ſinful and miſerably miſtaken men? yet this they muſt do that will call back the late Government</p>
            <p>Tell me, you that are ſick of this Revolution, with what kind of Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments do you juſtifie to your ſelves, the falſe, blaſphemous, and ungodly Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrins of <hi>Rome?</hi> What Arts, what Devices, can you think ſufficient to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade thoſe Souls which know themſelves freed by the Blood of Chriſt, to ſerve him in Righteouſneſs and Holineſs, to practiſe ſuch a voluntary Humility as to ſubject themſelves in all their Concerns, as well Spiritual as Temporal, to the Superſtition and Idolatry, to the Pride and ſinful Traditions of the Man of Sin? Have you had your Bibles too long, and now grow weary of them; and ſo out of Policy for your eaſe, would let in that Religion which muſt (in its own defence) take them from you? Are you ſo angry with Prayers becauſe Common, and in your Mother Tongue, that you long for ſuch as are ſtrange and in an unknown Tongue, ſuch as the Prieſt alone (and ſometimes not he neither) underſtands? Have two Sacraments been thought too many and bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſome by ſome of you, and will ſeven be lighter? But ſuch of you as have a due Veneration for both, how will you approve it when you ſhall ſee them Celebrated contrary to their Primitive Inſtitution? Inſtead of being uſed as Conduits of Grace, they are made Inſtruments of Rebellion, Blood and Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty. You that are now aſham'd to acquaint your loving, your grave and pious Paſtor, with the ſins which gall and trouble your Conſciences, how will you like it, when compell'd to confeſs all, even the ſmalleſt infirmity, to a cunning Prieſt, who ſhall make Merchandiſe of your Guilt, and Tyrannize over you from the knowledge of your weakneſs? Yet thus muſt you have put your Heads under their Girdles, had not this happy Revolution reliev'd you</p>
            <p>You who think it much to joyn with the Publick in an humble and penitent Confeſſion, and together with them receive the benefit of Abſolution, how will you take it to be ſent on tedious Pilgrimages, leaving in the mean while your deareſt concerns a prey to their Will, who ſhew you ſo little mercy? How will you like of building Hoſpitals, while your own Houſes are ready to drop upon your Heads? Will it pleaſe you to give the Sweat of your Brows, and the hard labour of your Hands, to fatten and pamper your Ghoſtly Father, and in the mean while ſee your Children ſtarve? and yet in this expectation they were come over How will you like it to have thoſe Wives (upon whom you fear the publick Examples are too prevalent) to be opportunely converſant with perſons whoſe Religion prohibits lawful, but tolerates unlawful enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments? Who declare a Prieſt may not Marry, but yet may keep a Whore; and ſo they do where-ever they come.</p>
            <p>How will it pleaſe you to ſee your Sons, which might have grown up as Plants, the Strength and Ornament of their Country, ſeduced into Monaſteries<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Where nurſed up in Ignorance, Plenty and Idleneſs, they become fitted for all
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:48382:4"/>
manner of wickedneſs? How will you like it to ſee your Daughters cooped up in Nunneries; than which Seraglio's have been more Chaſte: where inſtead of being like poliſh'd Corners of the Temple, ſhining in Knowledge, Grace and Vertue, they ſerve as Pillars for the wanton Prieſts to hang the Trophies of their Luſts upon?</p>
            <p>You now have the Word in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon; you have the Touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone in your hands to try the Spirits of the Prophets by, then you muſt expect but little of this nature; peradventure a recital of ſome pretended Saints Life taken out of the Legend: And as for the truth of all things, your ſhort and eaſie way muſt be without further examination, to believe as the Church be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves. Thus you muſt have pinn'd your Faith upon the Prieſts Sleeve, had the Abdicated King continued.</p>
            <p>Conſider the horrid Cruelties of the Inquiſition; peruſe the Martyrologies; call to mind the frequent and bloody Maſſacres made by this Religion. You that are ſo fond to live under a Popiſh Government, hear what you muſt then expect! And yet to all theſe things we were condemned. Was not this there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore occaſion ſufficient to wiſh and pray for the time of our Redemption; to believe and ſpeak honourably of this Revolution? Yet have I not related the one half of thoſe inſufferable Grievances in reſpect of Religion, under which we muſt have lingred out a moſt miſerable Life. He muſt be a Papiſt inwardly (notwithſtanding all his ſpecious pretences) who admires, ſpeaks and wiſhes for ſuch an adminiſtration again.</p>
            <p>Another occaſion requiring and urging forward this Revolution, was the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olation of our Laws.</p>
            <p>Nothing more fully demonſtrates the Wiſdom, Piety and Juſtice of a Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, nor redounds more to the honour of a Prince, than the enacting and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting of good and wholſome Laws: Theſe are the Cement which preſerves not only ſmaller Bodies, but the Univerſe from diſſolution: The Goods of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Fortune, All the Comforts of Life are no longer pleaſant to their poſſeſſors, than the Laws are had in Veneration. It is one of the greateſt Plagues of War, that it drowns the Voice of the Law: What then can we ſay in excuſe for the late notorious Violation of them? What could be expected leſs than an inundation of miſeries, when the Fence was demoliſhed, and Mens Luſts and Paſſions ran ſo high?</p>
            <p>To that paſs were things brought, that thoſe very Laws which gave the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſecurity to our Religion and Liberty, to our Lives and Fortunes, were upon Repealing; and they lay under the Cenſure of Prophane and Diſloyal, who did not with the greateſt Induſtry ſeek and propoſe their Aboliſhing. That humane Laws ſhould be thus trampled on, was but a Natural Conſequence to that boldneſs offered the Divine.</p>
            <p>Amongſt the many Laws of <hi>England</hi> none more notable (or at leaſt our dreadful Circumſtances did ſo repreſent it) than ſuch as prohibit a ſtanding Force to be raiſed by the Prince, without the Conſent and Concurrence of his Parliament: And have not our Eyes ſeen this ſnapt as Love? Was not a Body of Men rais'd and diſciplin'd after ſuch a manner, that they were much fitter to be the Agreſſors than Defenders of their Country; to deſtroy, than guard the Peace and Liberty of the Nation? If our Throats muſt be Cut, better by our Enemies than Fellow-Subjects.</p>
            <p>Our Laws have made proviſion, not only for the Princes Royal Prerogative, but likewiſe for Subjects juſt Right; yet how ſtrangely was the later ſwallowed
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:48382:4"/>
up of the former, and the bare pleaſure of the late King ſignified to the All-complying Judges, was of power to diſſeiſe the Subject of his Birth-right. 'Tis as good to have nothing, as no Right to what we have.</p>
            <p>The Laws of <hi>England</hi> preſcribe due Limits to the Regal Power; but in our days, as if the Throne had been ſick of a Tympany, all Bounds and Meaſures grew ſo uneaſie, that the reaſonable and modeſt way of Addreſſing, if it ſuited not with the Deſigns of Court, was termed Diſloyal; and ſo bad a Name was next door to hanging. It is hard to bear Oppreſſion; but moſt ſevere, not to be allow'd the liberty of declaring, and by honeſt and lawful means ſeek a redreſs.</p>
            <p>They muſt be perverſly ignorant of the Conſtitutions of <hi>England,</hi> who dare to juſtifie an unlimited Power, and Arbitrary Proceedings. Theſe perſons de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy both the Nature and End of Government.</p>
            <p>Self-preſervation firſt induc'd the aſſociating of private Perſons and Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, who agreed upon one common Intereſt, and upon a joynt Defence, againſt the Pride and Ambition of their encroaching Neighbours, who were too po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent for them ſingle and divided; and this Mother-Wit was ſo well approved, that in proceſs of time it occaſioned the Uniting and Incorporating of greater Companies; which deliberately choſe themſelves by way of ſtipulation, a Chief, expecting from him Defence and Protection, engaging to him Honour, Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute and Preheminence. It was not long ſince, that in the Title of the Engliſh Kings, might have been read in room of <hi>Jure haereditario, electione populi,</hi> which I ſuppoſe was eraſed, to make way for a ſtrange gloſs upon the Doctrins of Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive Obedience and Non reſiſtance.</p>
            <p>They that pretend to abſolute Monarchy, deſtroy as well the End as Original of Power. For whereas the good of the governed is thereby chiefly intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, theſe Men have nothing further in their eye, than gratifying the Will, Luſt and Pleaſure of the perſon governing. This is a ſtate ſo intolerable, that ſuch as plead moſt earneſtly for it, did they wiſely perpend the great variety of Mens Humours, the many unlucky Contingencies to which Human Life lies obnoxious, they would ſoon perceive the inſtability of their preſent favour, and conclude themſelves in danger of the greateſt Slavery; but admit we ſhould allow, ſufficient proviſion was made for themſelves under ſuch a Tyranny, yet what have they (by crying up this <hi>Diana</hi>) done for their Poſterity? What aſſurance have they, that the Rod the Father hath made, ſhall not ſcourge the Son? It is Vanity in the higheſt degree, to promiſe our ſelves the enjoyment of our Fathers, or our own Labour and Induſtry; when that the Laws them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, which are our only ſecurity, cannot keep <hi>Ahab</hi> out of <hi>Naboth</hi>'s Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard when minded to enter</p>
            <p>The <hi>Leviathan</hi> is ſaid to be made to take his paſtime in the Sea; the Ocean is large and deep, and fitted as it were for his Recreation; but to think or ſay, that myriads of People, whole Countries and Kingdoms were by God created for any ſingle perſon to execute his Will and Pleaſure on without controul, I conceive would much derogate from the Wiſdom, Juſtice and Goodneſs of God, eſpecially when we conſider ſuch perſons as they ſtand related to the Son of God by their Chriſtian Profeſſion; they that are in love with abſolute Power, I perſwade my ſelf, a ſhort change with a Subject of <hi>France</hi> would quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cure their madneſs.</p>
            <p>It muſt be diſmal to the tender heart of a Chriſtian, to think how cheap the Blood and Lives of Men grew, and what multitudes of Souls contrary to Law,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:48382:5"/>
were ſacrificed to the Idols of Popery and Arbitrary Power: Bleſſed be God, theſe high places are pulled down, and none in their Wits can wiſh their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoration.</p>
            <p>The Engliſh Laws provide, that the good be rewarded, and the bad puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; conſequently inequality in diſpenſing Rewards and Puniſhments, muſt cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate great confuſion; yet have the honeſt and upright, the truly Religious and Loyal, been Brow-beaten, diſcarded from Employments, burdened with Fines and Impriſonments, branded with Ignominy and Shame, and not a few done to death, while the Childrens Bread hath been given to Dogs, while Villains and Varlets, who have neither regarded God nor Man, Religion nor Honeſty, farther than their particular Intereſts, have been ſtrangely exalted to the higheſt Favour and Preferment, have been born out in their haughtineſs, cruelty, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudence and injuſtice.</p>
            <p>My Diſcourſe would extend too far, ſhould I enumerate every particular Law which lately felt the irreſiſtable Force of Popery and Tyranny; as the bringing in of the Pope's Nuncio, which is ſo palpable Treaſon, that upon the firſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion a wiſe Lord withdrew from Counſel, reſolving to have no hand in an Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fair ſo directly contrary to the Laws, and of ſo fatal a Conſequence to the Good of his Country I might likewiſe inſiſt in calling to Council a profeſſed Prieſt, and multitudes of the like Violations, but ſhall mention but one more, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Law of Rights, whereby Proviſion is made that every individual Perſon peacefully obtain and enjoy what ever of Right belongs to him; yet I believe ſince the World ſtood, was not this Law leſs valu'd than lately; witneſs the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpending, Removing and Impriſoning divers Honourable and Worthy Perſons; but above all, that notorious Attempt of impoſing an Heir upon theſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, the Prejudices hereby intended to the next Heir and Nation were num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berleſs; not only defrauding the rightful Heireſs, but tranſlating the Diadem out of the Family; this was the ready way to involve theſe Kingdoms in Blood and War, to extirpate our Religion, to confound all Foreign Alliance, to facili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the French Conqueſt, to enſlave a Free People; and that this was ſo done, matter of Fact doth teſtifie.</p>
            <p>And ſeems it not ſtrange to every ſober and thinking Perſon, to hear ſome at this day exclaiming, Why is not the Prince of <hi>Wales</hi> prov'd an Impoſtor? I anſwer this Queſtion with another, Why was not that care taken which the Law required to vindicate and clear his Birth? But whoſo diſcreetly reflects upon the management of this matter, will obſerve ſo much Providence in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founding the Counſel of the Wiſe, and ſo much Confidence in themſelves and Projects, as ſpoil'd the whole Contrivance, by their prepoſterous Boaſting of Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Events; the variety of times on which the ſuppoſed Conception was Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered; and that in Defiance to the Judgment of the ableſt Phyſicians, who from the Infirmities of the Queen had long before concluded a living Birth im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible; their pretended Spirit of Prophecy declared them Liars, who aſſerted a Male iſſued, and rejoyced for it publickly in ſome remote Countries of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> before the Queen knew any thing of it: (But yet this miſtake was par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donable in this regard, that the Age of the Infant would allow it) The Diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of places appointed for this Royal Delivery; the next Heirs being not call'd; what were at Hand were ſent out of the way; the eaſie pains; the Conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency of the Room; the Religion and Intereſt of the Midwife, and other At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendants; the drawn Curtains intercepting the Few Nobles then in preſence from hearing or beholding; and at laſt, when to ſatisfie the Nation as was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:48382:5"/>
the beſt of their Strength, the ſtrongeſt of their Vouchers were called, ſome were Foreigners, ſome of ſlender and mean Fortunes; not a Perſon, whoſe Religion, Intereſt or common Converſation did not directly oppoſe all Credence: And after all theſe, is there any neceſſity to make farther Trouble of a thing of nothing? So far did it conduce to ſettle the Crown, to the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsful carrying on of their Deſigns, that had the thing been real, had the Queen truly conceived, had ſhe gone her time, had ſhe had ſtrength to bring forth, we ſhould have had better Atteſtants, neither <hi>Seath, Bath,</hi> nor <hi>Tower</hi> had kept any from ſeeing their future hopes diſappointed: But their Fear and Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of the Evil intended, adviſed againſt calling too many and too honeſt Witneſſes to a palpable Forgery. Why do Men now wonder to ſee the Crown, by the over-ruling Providence of God, fallen from his Head, who in his Heart through a blind Zeal intended to rob his Family thereof? Let ſuch weigh well theſe things, that deſire ſo paſſionately a return of Times. What Safety, when the Laws are of no Force? It is full as ſecure to dwell among Rogues and Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lains, who hate all Law; as among them whoſe Laws, though never ſo good are of no further efficacy than the Will of one ſingle Perſon gives way.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The means by which this Revolution was brought about, were great, juſt, and moderate.</p>
            <p>So great, we muſt principally attribute it to the Divine Providence; ſo juſt, that no rational Objection can be made againſt it; ſome colourable Stories are buz'd about, which are wholly inconſiſtent with Reaſon, the Law of Nature, or thoſe of the Kingdom; ſo moderate, that never was leſs Blood or Violence known in working ſo ſignal a Deliverance.</p>
            <p>The Providence of God was viſible, in that, although the Kings of the Earth ſtood up, and the Rulers took Counſel together for our utter overthrow, and that their Projects were permitted ſo far to ſucceed, as might diſcover the malicious Intentions of their Authors, and convince us that our Ruin was by them concluded, yet were they blaſted before they attain'd their deſired matu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity: What could effect this? What could ſnatch a Prey out of the Jaws of Deſtruction, but the powerful hand of Heaven? Providence was likewiſe ſeen in that wonderful Chriſtian Patience then exerciſed by the Subjects in general, notwithſtanding ſuch manifeſt and important Provocations, as when an illegal Army was conſtantly inſulting over them, their Charters pull'd and command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from them, when all hopes of Juſtice were excluded, when ſuch Perſons were put into all places of Truſt, whether Sacred, Civil, and Military, as had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bin'd to ſet up a Power, and introduce a Religion, which muſt inevitably and ſpeedily confound all: As none but God alone could beſtow ſuch a wonderful Patience, ſo nothing but this Patience could have preſerv'd them for a Revoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; for the leaſt Offence given, the Hereditary Title had changed to that of Conqueſt. When all had been loſt, as our Enemies deſired and expected, this Patience did ſuppreſs Choler, though not Fear; it kept the Tongue from revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, though not the Heart from trembling; the Hand quiet, tho the Ear was daily alarm'd.</p>
            <p>Such admirable Patience, ſuch modeſt Submiſſion would have turn'd the Heart of any Father to the Children, had not the cruel Jeſuit prepoſſeſſed it; and to prevent all opportunities of doing Juſtice, and ſhewing Mercy, ſucceſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully advis'd againſt tolerating Addreſſes.</p>
            <p>Man's Extremity is uſually Heaven's Opportunity; and when among us all humane Help failed, then did he that ſitteth in Heaven, (and alſo ruleth in the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:48382:6"/>
Kingdoms of Men) ſtand up to help theſe meek and oppreſſed Kingdoms: It was from God that counſel came, (ſeeing the preſent Poſſeſſor inexorable) to apply to the next Heir, who ſtood bound in Conſcience to appear in Their Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, who were both Chriſtians, and part of his Inheritance; nor could he poſſibly connive at their waſte and ruin, unleſs reſolv'd upon his own Diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Damage. To his <hi>R. H.</hi> therefore the Nobles and Gentry of each De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree and Quality ſpeed away their Humble Petition, ſuch a large Deſcription of ſo many various and intollerable Sufferings as they were conſtrained to give, ſet his Heroick Blood on fire. His own particular danger was not ſo much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, as our timely Preſervation; and he reſolutely and generouſly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes the juſt Defence of the Forlorn, and them that had no Helper. Who doubts the Hand of the Almighty in this bleſſed Revolution? Who elſe could incline the <hi>Dutch</hi> (a People naturally jealous of their Liberty and Intereſt; a People highly diſoblig'd by Acts of Hoſtility and open Wars, by our unkind deſerting them in their neceſſity) to put forth the utmoſt of their Strength un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Princes Conduct in order for our Relief? It was the Righteous God who would not ſuffer the Debt contracted in the days of Q. <hi>Elizabeth</hi> to be longer unpaid.</p>
            <p>Farther, When theſe were Landed, what became of the Courage of the Standing Army? Who fill'd them with that Conſternation, as to turn back in the day of Battle? Did not their Guilty Conſciences apprehend theſe Succours to be as the Armies of the Living God, againſt whom it was in vain to make Reſiſtance?</p>
            <p>What more juſt Propoſals could a Prince ſo highly concern'd, after ſo great Advantages obtain'd, offer. Than that all Matters might be accomodated by the great Council of the Nation, a Parliament free from all manner of Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption and Prejudice? Father <hi>Peters</hi> had Chriſtned their cruel, bloody and unjuſt doings by the Name of <hi>Doing God good Service.</hi> But now the Man, whoſe Eyes this unexpected help had opened, ſaw how Religious ſoever Holy Mother Church might ſtyle them, yet they were not juſtifiable; and therefore ſo dreaded the Examination, that he judg'd it greater Prudence to Abdicate the Realm, than be detected.</p>
            <p>The Flock is in great Danger when the careleſs Shepherd deſerts it, but in greater when he angrily devotes it to the Ravenous Wolf: And that we were not a Prey, the greateſt Thanks are due to Heaven for ſending us ſo ſeaſonable a Deliverance.</p>
            <p>As for Moderation, What greater could be ſhewn in every Tranſaction, than what was at this time common? Eſpecially if we regard how deſperate our Caſe was; neither the Perſon of the late K. <hi>J.</hi> nor any of his Attendants ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered the leaſt Violence, more than what the preſent Circumſtances (of which they knew the Authors) made neceſſary, or their own indiſcreet ſtiffneſs pull'd upon them.</p>
            <p>When a blind Zeal and boundleſs Ambition ſhall change the Hearts of Princes, ſo that they have no regard, no pity, no care or concern for the Safety and Well-being of their People; theſe Tranſports render them uncapable of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing their Government. This was once the Judgment of Crowned Heads, when they were conſulted in the Caſe of <hi>Portugal,</hi> whoſe King became ſo fren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zical, as to kill his Subjects in ſport, and without due Proceſs of Law. What greater Madneſs can a Prince poſſibly be guilty of, Than to deſtroy and waſte his People, to rob them of their Antient and Lawful Priviledges, to bear that
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:48382:6"/>
mortal hatred to their Religion (though by Laws eſtabliſhed) as to Sacrifice the Profeſſors to extinguiſh the Profeſſion?</p>
            <p>The Government of <hi>England</hi> is certaily Feodatory, and the Solemn Oaths ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by our Kings at their Coronation, to Govern according to Law, has ſo much more than a Ceremony, that from thence riſes the Subjects Homage and Fealty. Who knows not that one part of the Covenant being broken, all Obligations of keeping the other ceaſes? No Reaſon to cry out, <hi>There is Treachery, O</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haziah, when he that exclaims is to himſelf the greateſt Traytor.</p>
            <p>This Revolution in the main depended upon the Divine Pity and Commiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; the outward Cauſes thereunto moving were, The Change of Religion, Violation of Laws, Deſerting the Throne, repairing to the profeſſed Enemy of the State, ſeeking and employing Foreign Force to enſlave a Free People. Had not theſe things been, K. <hi>J.</hi> might have now been at <hi>Whitehall,</hi> and have been Lord of all true Engliſh Hearts and Affections: But what Heart can truly love, or Hand fight for that Governor that they are ſure will deſtroy them We have better Eyes, and cannot like Mocks, adore that Light which will e're long conſume us.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Advantages attending this Revolution are both as great and as many as either our Neceſſities require, or our Curioſity can invent? In ſhort, Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion (with which no worldly Conſideration is worthy to ſtand in Competition) is by ſecured to us and our poſterity. The King that now Reigns, is not only fleſh of our fleſh, and bone of our bone, and ſo our Natural Liege Lord; but of our Religion alſo; and ſo he ought to be the more dear, as we are the more ſafe: Our Laws are once more Sacred, our Priviledges allow'd, our Rights aſſerted; and could we be ſo happy as to be reconciled to God by an hearty Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and an honeſt Reformation; could we unite and agree among our ſelves, we are bleſt with a King, who by his Proweſs, Wiſdom, Juſtice and Goodneſs, will make us as Great, as Glorious, as Happy, and as Dreadful as ever.</p>
            <p>Some there are (whoſe ſuppoſed numbers are not ſo dreadful as their pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices Helliſh) which are induſtrious to perſwade weak and unthinking perſons into a belief of glorious times to ſucceed the Reſtoration of the Abdicated King; and by cunning and fair words they do beguile ſome unſtable perſons, and draw them from their proper and ſafer Allegiance. I would beg the ſeduced, or they that are in danger ſo to be, to conſider the Vanity of theſe Propoſals, by reflect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the perſons who prefer them: Obſerve how they exult upon every ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of the <hi>French;</hi> and are never better pleaſed than in the danger of their Native Country: It is plain, they are of a ſervile Nature, and fitted for the Yoke; and the caſe properly in their eſteem, is not ſo much whether King <hi>W.</hi> or <hi>J.</hi> ſhall be King, as that the King of <hi>France</hi> may become our Maſter: Pitiful ſpirited Wretches, that ſell their Liberty, their Country, for a little Gold, to a Monſtrous Tyrant!</p>
            <p>It is notoriouſly known how diſaffected the Subject is in general, to all thoughts of a voluntary recalling a King, whoſe Ambition, Wrath and Cruelty, have been ſo dreadful: When re-inveſted with Power, what ſhall prevent a ſharp Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge? If our <hi>Metropolis</hi> was ſacrific'd in Flames to gratifie the Pride and Envy of aſpiring <hi>Rome,</hi> nothing leſs than enſlaving the Land, a Confiſcation of Eſtates, and a general Victim of poor Proteſtants, can attone the Wrath which now is incens'd. Which of all the Advocates for ſo deſperate a Cauſe, dare ſay the late King's Zeal for Popery is abated, that his Thirſt for an unlimited Power
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:48382:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
is aſſwag'd, that he has wean'd himſelf from the influence of Jeſuitical Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, that Juſtice and Equity, Truth and Mercy, that the good Honour and Welfare of the Realm, is any more his delight than ever? ſo ſhort, if any Voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, rarely makes ſuch an happy alteration, eſpecially on them who Travel where they ſee no Preſidents to rectifie their former miſapprehenſions.</p>
            <p>Since therefore ſo little hope of a return is to be expected from the abus'd Affection of his People; by what other means can he force his re-entry, except the <hi>French</hi> aſſiſtance? And it is probable, <hi>Lewis</hi> will with great Gallantry plead this Cauſe, till ſuch time as he ſhall ſee opportunity to ſet up his own; but ſhould we ſuppoſe that Generoſity in that extravagantly ambitious King, that he would but clear the way unto the Throne, and then draw off; yet muſt we believe, ſo great a Charge ſhall be demanded, as the whol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Wealth of the Kingdom can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not anſwer: Sure it were better Policy for us to unite, aid and aſſiſt him with a moyety, who will preſerve the reſt, by keeping ſuch Enemies out, and che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing and protecting us within our dear and native Country.</p>
            <p>It is ſufficient to make the Jollieſt Heart to bleed, to forethink ſuch troubles as muſt naturally follow, ſhould ſome wicked mens hopes be compleated: Our Religion muſt truckle to Popery; our Liberty muſt be exchang'd into Slavery; our Rights and Priviledges into Courteſie; our Law muſt be <hi>Nero</hi>'s Will; our Country and Trade muſt be a prey to Foreigners; our Wives the ſubject of their Luſt, our Children daſht againſt the Stones; humane Blood muſt waſh the Streets, and cleanſe the Land; and if Cruelty ſhall be weary before a thorough depopulation, the ſurviving will ſerve for Drudges and Laughing-Stocks: Nor let any flatter themſelves of greater ſecurity, in that they have been bred Sons of <hi>Rome,</hi> or that they have lately conform'd to that Religion. The fear of a Relapſe ſhall ſentence the laſt, and want of Zeal and action in the Cauſe, ſhall be the formers Doom: beſides, to ſupport a ſinking Cauſe, to animate Cruelty and Barbariſm, all the Eſtates, Lands and Livings of this Realm, are devoted as an Oblation to the Church, or a Reward to the Soldier. High time is it there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for all Engliſh Men to conſider, while they have Hands and Hearts, Power and Strength, couragiouſly to Aſſert and Defend the Juſtice of this Revolution, and in all thankfulneſs to God, and Loyalty to their Majeſties King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> to unite and ſtrengthen themſelves againſt the common Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my. They are incited by the Royal Example; they are encouraged by their own good and ſafety; they are compell'd to it, for <hi>Hannibal</hi> is now at the Gates.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
